Mss.B.L981
American Philosophical Society
- Papers
  - Letter to J. F. Royle, June 9, 1836; 7 1/2" x 4 1/2"; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    A.L.S. 2p. and add. Asks him to distribute some copies of his anniversary address. Originally B L981.1
  - Letter to [Benjamin] Silliman, June 14, 1836; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    Regarding Silliman's favorable impression of the 4th edition of Lyell's book.
  - Letter to Dr. [J.F.] Royle, Feb. 4, 1837; 7 1/4" x 4 1/2"; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    A.L.S. 3p. and add. Originally B L981.2
  - Letter to J[ames de Carle] Sowerby, Kentish Town, May 22, 1837; 7-1/2x4-1/2x; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    A.L.S. 1p. and add. Sends cardita and asks that it be sketched. Originally B L981.30
  - Letter to [Benjamin] Silliman, December 25, 1838; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    Regarding American copyrights and trans-Atlantic reprints of Lyell's work; English booksellers' practice of repackaging and marking up articles; the controversy of Harlan's Basilosaurus.
  - Letter to [] B. Wigham, Apr. 14, 1841; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    Returning a mastadon tooth and packet of fishes.
  - Letter to [Benjamin] Silliman, Feb. 6, 1842; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    Regarding lectures.
  - Letter to [Benjamin] Silliman, Feb. 22, 1842; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    Regarding existing stock of Lyell's book and his search for his next publisher.
  - Letter to L[ewis] J[acob] Cist, May 28, 1842; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    Schedule prevents Lyell from lecturing in Cincinnati.
  - Letter to S. Woodward, Jan. 5, 1843; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    Request for the return of his illustrations (including Niagara Falls) and New Jersey fossils.
  - Letter to Mr. Putnam, Jan. 13, 1843; 7-1/2x4-1/2; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    A.L.S. 2p. He is to send, and bill, Sir William Symonds the Michaux Sylva.
    Unlocated 2 March 2011.
  - Letter to Mr. Putnam, Jan. 19, 1843; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    Requesting a delivery to Capt. Sir. William Symonds, currently out of town.
  - Letter to S. Woodward, Feb. 3, 1843; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    Request for illustrations (Stigmaria clays of Pennsylvania) sent in a letter read to the Geological Society.
  - Letter to C. Manley, May 8, 1843; 7 1/4" x 4 1/2"; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    A.L.S. 1p. Previous engagement prevents his attendance at a meeting. Originally B L981.6
  - Letter to S. Woodward, June 12, 1845; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    Sorry to have missed Woodward at the previous evening's meeting of the Geological Society.
  - Letter to [Benjamin] Silliman, Apr. 26, 1846; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    Regarding New Hampshire mountains.
  - Letter to B[enjamin] Silliman, May 8, 1846; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    Regarding publication.
  - Letter to John Kempe (?), Dec. 6, 1846; 7-1/4x4-1/2; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    A.L.S. 3p. and end. On the co-existence of man and the megatherium. Originally B L981.32
  - Letter to [?], Dec. 8, 1846; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    Fragment.
  - Letter to Lady [Marion Shaw] Bell, Feb. 11, 1847; 7x4-1/4; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    A.L.S. 2p. Says that Matheson will vote for her candidate. Originally B L981.23
  - Letter to J[oshua] T[oulmin] Smith, July 6, 1847; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    Appreciates Smith's paper on the formation of chalk flints.
  - Letter to [?], Jan. 11, 1848; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    Regarding Dr. Hooker's mountain climbing in the Himalayas and fatalities in the party.
    Hooker, Joseph Dalton, Sir, 1817-1911
  - Letter to "My dear Sir", Dec. 5, 1848; 7-1/4x4-1/4; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    A.L.S. 4p. Concerning the division of estates upon the death of the father, in the U.S. as contrasted with Great Britain and France. Refers to John Jacob Astor's will. Originally B L981.33
  - Letter to Lieut. Davis, Cambridge, Jan. 11, 1849; 7-1/4x4-1/2; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    A.L.S. 3p.and end. Concerning his work on geology and tidal activity. Has submitted his theories to the Geological Society. Originally B L981.28
  - Letter to [Joseph Green?] Cogswell, March 6, 1849; 7-1/4x4-1/2; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    A.L.S. 4p. Will bring letters and hopes to see him. His MS on the U.S. (not geological) is going to the printers., and wishes that Cogswell read it and forward it to the publisher. Originally B L981.20
  - Letter to Madame Van der Weyer, Sept. 20, 1850; 7-1/4x4-1/2; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    A.L.S. 2p. Asks that scientific publications be forwarded. Originally B L981.33
  - Letter to "My dear Sir", Feb. 18, 1851; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    Suffering from a cold; rules for signing certificates, voting procedures; rough sketches of flints discovered in Belgium.
  - Letter to R. Dunn, Apr. 27, 1851; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    Apologies for missing invitation, as he was in Dosetshire at the time.
  - Letter to [John Thomas] Quekett, Nov. 2, 1851; 7x4-1/2; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    A.L.S. 3p. and end. Friendly letter. Concerning Richard Owen. Concerning bats.
  - Letter to J[ohn] Chapman, March 27, 1852; 7-1/4x4-1/4; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    Harley St., A.L.S. 1p. Sends ticket for lecture, but asks that it be returned, if unused. Originally B L981.22
  - Letter to ----, June 15, 1852; 7" x 4 1/2"; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    A.L.S. 3p. Originally B L981.3
  - Letter to Dr. Dunn, Mar. 14, 1853; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    Sorry to have missed Dunn's paper on craniology, offers tickets for Lyell's own lecture.
  - Letter to Dr. Carpenter, Mar. 21, 1853; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    Cannot attend party due to a prior engagement at Murchison's; wishes to share a drawing of a shell and fish's tooth.
  - Letter to J. [R.] Ingersoll, Mar. 26, 1853; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    Regarding the disposition of three copies of Owens's geological report (Geological Society, Museum of Economic Geology, and the Library of the Royal Society); Lyell and Murchison have each received a copy.
  - Letter to C[harles] W[entworth] Dilke, Oct. 31, 1853; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    Regarding the distribution of a draft report.
  - Letter to A[lexander] D. Bache, Nov. 9, 1853; 7-1/4x4-1/2; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    London, A.L.S. 4p. Concerning a geological exhibition. Geology and an expedition for study of geology of the Canary Islands. Refers to Hilgard, Hall and Walker. Originally B L981.24
  - Letter to J. Smith, Oct. 8, 1855; 7" x 4 1/4"; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    London, A.L.S. 3p. Sends copy of a lecture. Originally B L981.11
  - Letter to the Editors of the Athenaeum, March 10, 1856; 7x4-1/2; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    A.L.S. 2p. and add. Concerning publication of his talk before the Royal Institution. Originally B L981.31
  - Letter to Rev. I. Barlow., Jan. 22, 1857; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    Regretfully declines invitation.
  - Letter to S[amuel Pickworth] Woodward, British Museum, March 16, 1857; 7x4-1/4; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    A.L.S. 13p. and add. Concerning rocks and fossil shells of Madiera and Canary Islands and age of the islands. Sends list of shells. Refers to Wollaston. Originally B L981.19
  - Letter to Major Becker, Oct. 31, 1858; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    Thanks for the geological maps.
  - Letter to "My dear Sir", May 11, 1859; 7x4-1/4; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    A.L.S. 1p. Concerning the publication of his Etna paper by the Berlin Geological Society. Originally B L981.33
  - Letter to Sir Benjamin [Brody], May 30, 1859; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    In support of Dr. Charles Murchison for the post of Superintendant of the Millbank Penitentiary.
  - Letter to [?], June 3, 1859; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    Name of recipient sliced out. Regarding fossils in Lower vs. Upper Green Sand, which may have implications for Lyell's work.
  - Letter to H[enry] J[ohn] S[tephen] Smith, June 13, 1859; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    Regarding travel and meeting logistics.
  - Letter to ----, Nov. 19, 1859; 7" x 4 1/4"; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    London, A.L.S. 2p. Cave animals. Originally B L981.10
  - Letter to [?], Jan. 24, 1860; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    Has received flint implements.
  - Letter to G[eorge Musgrave] Musgrave, June 8, 1860; 7x4-1/4; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    A.L.S. 2p. Concerning a fossil oyster. Originally B L981.17
  - Letter to ----, July 24, 1860; 7x4-1/2; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    London, A.L.S. 1p. Has received flint implements and thinks more will be found. Originally B L981.27
  - Letter to A[lbert] Way, Aug. 9, 1860; 5-1/2x4-1/4; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    Rudolstadt, Germany, A.L.S. 3p. Antiquity of man, in Liege caves, and other locations. Concerning an argument at "your archaeological meeting." Originally B L981.18
  - Letter to W. White, Dec. 2, 1861; 7" x 4 1/2"; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    A.L.S. 2p. Desires to borrow certain works from the library. Originally B L981.9
  - Letter to [Henry] Bence Jones, July 25, 1862; 7x4-1/2; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    A.L.S. 2p. Refuses invitation since he is trying to finish a book. Expects to hear Huxley. Originally B L981.21
  - Letter to E. Belfour, Jan. 27, 1863; 6" x 3 3/4"; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    A.L.S. 1p. Asks him to call a meeting of the Hunterian trustees. Originally B L981.12
  - Letter to J. Timbe, Feb. 23, 1863; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    Timbe portraits are "very truthful" and Lyell wishes to buy a copy of the bok.
  - Letter to Dr. [William ?] Sharpey, Feb. 26, 1863; 5 3/4" x 4 1/2"; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    A.L.S. 3p. Correction of one of his works. Originally B L981.8
  - Letter to G[eorge] P[oulett Thomson] Scrope, April 29, 1863; 7x4-1/2; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    A.L.S. 6p. Concerning disputes with Falconer and Prestwick. Concerning a publication of his. Originally B L981.16
  - Letter to H. Dixon, May 30, 1863; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    Sending Col. Byrne's memoir of the Irish Rebellion.
  - Letter to S. W. Symonds, July 7, 1863; 7" x 4 1/2"; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    London, A.L.S. 5p. Coexistence of man with elephants. Itinery for a geological trip. Originally B L981.14
  - Letter to H[enry] W. Bates, Mar. 4, 1864; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    Regarding Bates's book.
  - Letter to W[alter] White, Mar. 5, 1864; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    Wishes to borrow Heer's Flora Tertiaria Helvetica from the Royal Society.
  - Extract from the Proceedings of the Geological Quarterly (vol. 13, 1857, pp. 212ff.), March 16, 1864; 5-1/2x6-3/4; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    A.D.S. 1p. Fragment. Originallly B L981.33
  - Letter to Mr. Murch (?), May 7, 1864; 7x4; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    London, A.L.S. 4p. Concerning the British Association for the Advancement of Science. Originally B L981.29
  - Letter to [?], July 13, 1864; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    Regarding Dr. Roger's travel to Bath.
  - Letter to "My dear Sir", Aug. 9, 1864; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    Hoping to get the U.S. Minister to attend an upcoming meeting.
  - Letter to [Sir John?] Evans, May 20, 1865; 7x4-1/2; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    A.L.S. 2p. Concerning Nilsson's comments on Crawford's paper on Stonehenge, to be read at the Ethnological Society of London. Originally B L981.33
  - Letter to [Francis] Galton, Aug. 8, 1865; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    Regarding travel.
  - Letter to Dr. [William ?] Sharpey, Nov. 25, 1865; 7" x 4 1/2"; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    London, A.L.S. 3p. Mentions Darwin's Origin of species. Originally B L981.7
  - Letter to [Joseph Dalton] Hooker, Dec. 29, 1865; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    Note included with a forwarded enclosure from Sir Roderick Murchison.
  - Letter to [Charles] Moore, Jan. 4, 1866; 7" x 4 1/2"; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    [London] (?) A(?) L.S. 5p. Measurement of geological time. Comments on Croll's work. Originally B L981.m
  - Letter to [Charles] Moore, Jan. 24, 1866; 7" x 4 1/2"; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    [London] A(?) L.S. 4p. Encloses proof of his last edition of the Elements. Geological comments. Originally B L981.m
  - Letter to [Charles] Moore, May 1, 1866; 7" x 4 1/2"; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    [London] A (?)L.S. 6p. Appreciates aid given by Moore. Geological comments. Croll. Originally B L981.m
  - Letters to [Charles] Moore, Jan. 4, Jan. 24, May 1, Nov. 3, 1866, 1873; 7" x 4 1/2"; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    [London] A.L.S. and L.S. 4 pieces ca. Originally B L981.m
    2 November 1873 letter may be unlocated or may be the "My Dear Sir" letter - 2 March 2011
  - Letter to H[enry] W. Bates, Aug. 31, 1866; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    Asks Bates's opinion on Agassiz's "Valley of the Amazons" papers and conclusions at odds with what Lyell knows of the Mississippi valley and delta.
  - Letter to [Henry W. Bates], Sept. 2, 1866; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    Regarding Agassiz and South American glaciers.
  - Letter to [Henry W. Bates], Sept. 16, 1866; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    Regarding letters, shells, Stevens, and Agassiz.
  - Letter to ----, March 11, 1867; 8 1/4" x 5 1/2"; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    London, L.S. 2p. A new edition and translations of his works. Originally B L981.4
  - Letter to [E. T. Stevan], May 4, [1867?]; 7x4-1/2; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    London, A.L.S. 3p. His travel to Salisbury and hope to visit with him. Flint implements. Originally B L981.26
  - Letter to [Henry Walter Bates], Nov. 15, 1867; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    Regarding theories of racial distribution (particularly of "Red Indians").
  - Autograph, July 16, 1868; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    On a square of paper embossed with: 73, Harley St., London. W.
  - Letter to [John] Murray, August 4, 1869; Dufferin and Ava, Frederick Temple Blackwood, Marquis of, 1826-1902
    Letter of introduction to Dr. [Tincoffs?], pasted to the same sheet as a May 10 letter from Lyell.
  - Letter to [C. O. Groom Napier], Jan. 20, 1870; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    Praise for the recipient's book. The Book of Nature and the Book of Man, preface by Lord Brougham.
  - Letter to [S.V.Wood ?], June 20, 1872; 7" x 4 1/2"; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    London, A.L.S. 5p. Requests him to read certain passages in the new edition of his Antiquity of man. Came with Lyell's Geological evidences of the antiquity of man,London, 1873.
  - Letter to Searles Wood, June 22, 1872; 7" x 4 1/2"; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    London, A.L.S. 4p. Relative to the Antiquity of man. Came with Lyell's Geological evidences of the antiquity of man, London, 1873.
  - Letter to [Searles Wood ?], Sept. 23, 1872; 6" x 4"; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
  - Letter to Milne Home, Oct. 19, 1872; 7x4-1/2; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    London, A.L.S. 4p. Concerning Roman ruins and rise of land in Great Britain. Refers to Evans. Originally B L981.33
  - Letter to [David] Milne-Home, Dec. 9, 1872; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    Regarding Scottish boulders in Dr. Christison's address, treatment of post-Roman upheavals by Milne-Home and Geikie.
  - Letter to [David] Milne-Home, Dec. 16, 1872; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    Regarding Ramsay's 3rd edition of Physical Geology of Great Britain, which adopts Geikie's theories of laud despite conflicting evidence Lyell believes he brought to Ramsay's attention.
  - Letter to [David] Forbes, June 25, 1873; 7x4-1/2; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    London, A.L.S. 2p. Forwards an eloge. Originally B L981.33
  - Letter to ----, Nov. 3, 1873; 7" x 4 1/2"; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    London, L.S. 2p. Encloses passage in re the Rhoetic Labyrinthodonts. (This letter may be addressed to Charles Moore.) Originally B L981.m
  - Letter to [David] Forbes, Dec. 18, 1873; 4 1/2" x 7"; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    London, L.S. 2p. Sends additional chapters of a certain work for correction.
  - Letter to [Charles] Darwin, April 24, 1874; Enclosed in mylar sleeve.; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    Lyell's £25 pledge toward a Zoological Station.
  - Ticket to the Zoological Society's gardens, June 20, 1874
    Removed from B:AL1.2, 24 July 1975.
  - Letter to [A. W. Callcott], April 26, undated; 9x7-1/4; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    Athenaeum, A.L.S. 1p., end. Has asked for a paper by Mrs.Calcott and hopes it has not miscarried. Originally B L981.25
  - Letter to H[enry] W. Bates, March 26, undated; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    Invitation to dinner.
  - Letter to H[enry] W. Bates, March 31, undated; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    Regarding antipodean flora and fauna.
  - Letter to [John Murray?], May 10, undated; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    May 10 letter regarding books. Pasted to the same sheet as an August 4, 1869 introductory letter from Lord Dufferin.
  - Letter to "Dear [John Forbes] Royle", May 10, undated; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    Regarding Himalayan and European species of plants.
  - Letter to "My dear Sir", July 22, undated; 7-1/4x4-1/2; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    Monday, A.L.S. 1p. Hopes they can visit in town soon. Originally B L981.33
  - Letter to Sir John F. Herschel, December 29, undated; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    Invitation to attend a party.
  - Biographical note, undated; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    Written some time after October 31, 1874.
  - Concerning neolithic instruments, undated; 9x5-3/4; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    A.D. 2p. Fragment. Originally B L981.33
  - Letter to [Henry] Bence Jones, undated; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    Regarding a conversation with Farraday and Barnard about modifying a passage.
  - Letter to [William Benjamin] Carpenter, undated; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    Regarding a paper.
  - Letter to [Henri] Lecoq, undated; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    In French. Letter of introduction for Prof. Turner of London University, traveling to Auvergne to study French geology.
  - Letter to Milne Home, undated; 6x4; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    London. A.L.S. 4p. Sends manuscript of his projected work and hopes it meet with approval. Wishes Homes would get his article in print before he (Lyell) publishes. Originally B L981.33
  - Letter to [Sir Richard] Owen, undated; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    Fossil sample (small rodent jaw) discovered with the Mastadon.
  - Letter to Gen. Sabine, undated; 6 1/4" x 4"; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    A.L.S. 2p. Asks thet an invitation to the General's evenings be sent to the Rev. S.W. King. Originally B L981.13
  - Letter to M. Violet (?), undated; 8" x 5"; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    Wednesday morning. A.L.S.(?) 1p. and add. In French. Invitation to dinner. Originally B L981.5
  - Letter to S. Woodward, undated; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    Requests to borrow specimens for his lectures. Silurian fossils, including trilobite, chain coral, graptolite, lingula, lituite, pentamerus, porites, tentaculite, orthis, and "anything which occurs to you as useful."
  - Letter to "Dear Sir", Tuesday, undated; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    Request for a quarter-sized copy of a trilobite diagram in Owens's Geological Survey of Wisconsin.
  - Letter to "Dear Sir", undated; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    Accompanying a section of Martha's Vineyard, illustration for an upcoming paper.
  - Letter to ?, undated; Lyell, Charles, Sir, 1797-1875
    Regarding Norfolk cliffs.
  - Portrait of Lyell, undated
    Cut from a magazine.
    Separated Materials note
    Inadvertently separated from a file, circa 1865-73.